Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections, ca. 1198-1616
UCLA Library Special Collections
- The Charles E. Young Research Library: Department of Special Collections.
  - BOOK OF HOURS, use of Rome. France, s. XVIin., 170/26.; Parchment, ff. iii (paper) + 116 (includes f. 38bis) + 24 (paper, printed, s. XVI/XVII) + iii (paper); 152 × 97 (110 × 70) mm. 1-48 58(-3 and 6, after ff. 34 and 36) 68 78 (-3, after f. 47) 88 98(-8, after f. 67, canceled by the scribe) 10-158. 18 long lines; double bounding lines; ruled in pale brown or pink ink. Written by 1 rounded sophisticated humanistic bookhand imitating roman type; grayish ink. 2-line gold initials on red/blue, green/blue, or red/green squarish backgrounds, 1-line gold initials on alternately red, blue, green squarish backgrounds, highlighted with gold, 14- or 15-line spaces for illustration were reserved at the beginning of each section; some were filled with engravings from various sources, while others remain empty: f. 7 (Gospel of John), 4 small engravings are glued in, depicting a sainted bishop exorcising a man, the same (?) bishop seeing a vision of the Virgin and Child, a man with a halo being strung up on a pole, 3 men in long tunics being crucified; f. 9v (Hours of the Virgin), Annunciation, possibly of Germanic origin; f. 25v (Lauds), left empty; opening leaf of prime is missing; f. 37v (Terce), left empty; f. 40v (Sext), the Virgin and Child, standing on a crescent, in glory, from a different source from the preceding engravings; f. 44v (None), Pietà, surrounded by a rosary with the large beads showing the Five Wounds of Christ, possibly from the same source as the engraving on f. 7; opening leaf of vespers is missing; f. 54 (Compline), Coronation of the Virgin by 2 angels as she sits on a crescent with the Child in her lap, from the same source as the engraving on f. 40v; f. 68v (Penitential psalms), left empty; f. 84v (Office of the Dead), left empty; f. 112 (at the end of the text), Francis of Assisi receiving the stigmata from a vision of the crucifix (full page). The manuscript is bound with a printed text, S'ENSVYVENT LES VESPRES DV DIMENCHE ET DV SAMEDI avec Compile & les hymnes communes de l'annee; French, s. XVIex, 3 quires of 8, labeled Aa i-iiii, Bb..., Cc.. .; in roman types, with titles, headlines, initials printed in red. Water stains in the upper outer corners from f. 87 onward.; Bound in dark brown calf over paste boards. Gilt medallions (Crucifixion/ Annunciation) and the gilt inscriptions NICOLAS / NOVEL stamped on front/back covers respectively; gilt fore-edge; s. XVI/XVII.
    1) ff. 1-6v: Calendar with major entries in red; included are feasts of Rupert (27 March), Bernardinus, translation (17 May), Bernard[in]us (20 May), Medard (8 June), Amandus (25 June), Martialis (30 June), Our Lady of the Snow (5 August), Transfiguration (6 August), Louis of Toulouse (19 August), Vivianus (27 August), Nativity of the Virgin (8 September, in red), Maurilius (13 September), Lambert (17 September), Maurice (22 September), Francis of Assisi (4 October), Nicasius (11 October), Restitutus (3 November), Eligius (1 December); the following names were added later, apparently not intended as saints: Bernardus (10 March), Claudius (13 March), Petrus (14 March), Stephanus (23 March); also added in the lower margin of the same page, f. 2: Anna, Maria.
    2) ff. 7-9: Pericope of John [John 1:1-14] with versicle, response, and prayer, Protector deus in te sperantium... [P.F. Perdrizet, Le calendrier parisien... (Paris, 1933) p.25]; Oratio ad beatam mariam, O domina gloriae, O regina leticiae....
    3) ff. 9v-68 [rubric on f. 9]: Hore beate mariae virginis secundum usum romanum incipiunt feliciter; at matins variations of psalms for the week are set into the text before the lessons; suffrages to All Saints at the end of each hour from lauds to compline; 3 leaves are missing with loss of text following f. 34 (end of lauds and beginning of prime), f. 36 (the third psalm of prime), and f. 47 (end of none and beginning of vespers).
    4) ff. 68v-84 [rubric on f. 68]: Penitential psalms and litany, including John and Paul, and Peter, Berard de Carbio, Accursius, Adjustus, and Otho (the last five as one entry, the Franciscan martyrs) among the martyrs; Francis, Antony, Berard, Bernardinus, and Dominic among the religious; Geneviève and Elisabeth among the virgins.
    5) ff. 84-111v: Office of the Dead, use of Rome; ff. 112-115v ruled but blank, except for an engraving glued to f. 112 (see below).
    Written in France in the early sixteenth century. Belonged to the poet and friend of C.K. Ogden, Edward Harry William Meyerstein (1889-1952); his bookplate, dated 1911, on front pastedown. Acquired by UCLA soon after Meyerstein's death, source unknown.
    Secundo folio: [Calendar, f. 2] KL Martius habet; [Text, f. 8] sui eum non receperunt
  - MARTYROLOGY. Northern Italy, s. XV1., 170/43.; Parchment, ff. i (paper, modern) + ii (paper, s. XVI) + 95 (foliated iii-viii, 1-89) + i (paper, modern); 220 × 165 (152 × 115) mm. 16 2-910 1012(-10, 11, 12). Plain horizontal catchwords in the middle of the lower margin. 26 long lines, ff. 87-89v in 2 columns of 26 lines; ruling in lead. Rounded Italian gothic bookhand in current liturgical style (littera textualis formata); almost black ink. 2-line initials alternately red on blue penwork and blue on red penwork; initials in the text slashed with yellow. A few additions (s. XV-XVI) to the calendar and to the text: f. i top “Littera [dat]aria martyrologi. 1539 currebat littera .A., 1552 .0.,” by the same hand as f. iir-v, which also enters running titles on the recto top margin; f. i middle “MDXXXI” and (possibly the same hand) “Fratris Johannis Baptiste ... or. S. ob.”; f. iv “Questo martirologio serviva per la chiesa di Padova; si è incontrato con quello di Venezia del 1549 ad signum spei, quello Usuardo ed altri uniti da Giovanni Molano, Lovanii 1568, quello colle note del Baronio; e dove sono le linee di piombo indica non esservi nei sopradetti Martirologi cio che le linee notano. II tempo in cui è stato scritto pare dal 1400 al 143 < > e questo si cava da osservazione dei santi. Degno d'osservazione è il titolo che porta in fronte Incipit ordo datarii et come ancora, secondo I'uso anticho della Chiesa, principiando la vigilia di Natale” (s. XVII-XVIII; the codex shows throughout the marks of careful collation).; Bound in the original blind stamped leather (floral patterns, acorns and a typically Italian border with squarish rope motif) over wooden boards; traces of four clasps.
    1) f. iir-v: [Table of paschal terms, written in a sixteenth-century cursive hand] Terminum paschalem [sic], Post nonas martis ubi sit luna... dominica prima post 15 kal. maii.
    2) ff. iii-viiiv: [Calendar] Prima dies Iani timor est et septima vani... [Walther, Initia no.14561; other calendar verses at top and bottom of each month]; f. v IX Kal. Iun. Ver fugat Urbanus estatem Sinphorianus... [Walther, Initia no.20219].
    3) ff. 1-86v: In Christi nomine amen. Incipit ordo datarii sive martilogii secundum consuetudinem romane curie, IX Kal. Ianuarii, luna... Vigilia natalis domini. Apud Antiochiam Syrie ... [X Kal. Ian.] Sancti Servuli... miracula creberrimine [sic] fiunt. Et alibi plurimorum sanctorum martirum confessorum atque sanctarum virginum. Dic lector nonas sic ydus atque kalendas... magnanimiter substinentes eterne vite delitiis cum eodem et gloria indicibili potiuntur, cuius nos ipse participes faciat. Qui cum Patre et Filio et Spiritu sancto vivit et regnat in secula seculorum. Amen. Numerus quidem sanctorum hiis exceptis suma [sic] quorum / Solus sit rex angelorum... De quibus expertus solus Deus est sibi certus /[Q]ui sunt scribentis adiunctoresque legentis. Amen [Usuardi Martyrologium with additions; cf. PL vol.124.833-860, vol.123.601-992, vol.124.1-830].
    4) ff. 87-89v: [Temporal and sanctoral prayers, ending imperfectly] Dominica prima de adventu ad pretiosa. Lectio. Non in commessationibus et ebrietatibus ... In nativitate plurimorum martyrum. Fulgebunt iusti et tamquam scintile in arundineto discurent iu//.
    Written in the first half of the fifteenth century, in northern Italy to judge from the spelling. Added names of saints provide little help in localizing: f. v “vi Id. Madii sancti Cataldi episcopi et confessoris” (Cataldus, bp. of Taranto); f. vii “viii Id. Septembris sancti Sperandei confessoris” (cf. Sperandeo and Sperandea of Gubbio); f. v “sancti Bernardini confessoris ordinis minorum” (s. XVex; Bernardino da Siena was canonized in 1450). The manuscript presumably was in Padua in the seventeenth or eighteenth century (note on f. iv). Acquired by UCLA from an unknown source, before 1942 (accessioned in 1941).
    Secundo folio: [Calendar, f. iv] Martius apud hebreos; [Text, f. 2] Apud Ephesum natale
  - BREVIARY, 4 volumes in 3. Paris, s. XVmed., 170/49.; Fig. 19
    - Volume I.
      1) ff. 1-6v: [Calendar] Prima dies mensis et septima truncat ut ensis... [Walther, Initia 14563], including the feasts of Geneviève (3 January), William of Donjeon (10 January), Launomar (19 January), Bathildis and Radegundis (30 January), Vedast and Amandius (6 February); Honorina (27 February); Dionysius, invention (22 April); Eutropius (30 April); Medard and Gildard (8 June); Landericus, bishop (10 June); Leufred (21 June); Thuriaf (13 July); Philibert (20 August); Lupus and Chrodegang (3 September); Chlodoald and Evurtius (7 September); Audomar and Lambert (17 September); Dionysius, Rusticus, and Eleutherius (9 October); Gerald (13 October); Magloire (24 October); Edmund Rich (16 November); Susceptio reliquiarum of Dionysius (4 December).
      2) ff. 7-16v: [Ordinary] In anno quo nativitas... perducat nos regina angelorum amen.
      3) ff. 17-372va: Temporale, from I Dom. de adventu to Sabbato post Pentecosten; mutilated at the beginning, //princeps sodomorum percipite..., with a lacuna in Sabbato in vigilia Pasche; a leaf is missing between f. 293... qui missa celebratur a// and f. 294, //gaudia nunciavit, candor.. .; f. 372vb blank.
      4) ff. 373ra-430v: Psalter, mutilated at beginning and end, with lacunae: //contrivisti. Domini est salus... [f. 394v:|... commoventur pedes mei super// [f. 400:] //et tabescere fecisti... [f. 398v:]... sed speravit in multitu// [f. 399:] //et dixi quis dabit... [f. 403v:]... inequitate et gentes// [f. 404:] //tuarum respice in me... illic mandavit dominus benedice// [1 folio is missing at the beginning; the sequence of folios between ff. 394 and 404 is to be reconstructed as follows: f. 394, 1 f. missing, ff. 400, 395-398, 1 f. missing, ff. 399, 401-403, 1 f. missing, f. 404; Ps. 3.8-25, 53, 117, 118 [divided in the liturgical portions, with Antiphon, Oratory, Hymnal inserted in between], 29-37.17; 38.12-51.9; 54.7-66.5; 68.17-79; Canticum Moysis I, Exodus 15.1-19; Psalms 80-96; Canticum Abacuc, Habakkuk 3.2-19; Psalms 97-108; Canticum Moysis II, Deut. 32.1-43; Ps. 109-132.3; with Antiphon and Hymnal].
    - Volume II.
      1) ff. 1-398v: Sanctorale, beginning (mutilated) with the feast of Medard and Gildard (8 June) //ferret divinitatis sue igitur.... and ending with Catharine (25 November), Geneviève, de miraculo ardentium (26 November), and Presentation of the Virgin (21 November) out of sequence; the Feast of the Presentation was added belatedly to the Western liturgy, first celebrated in France in 1374, which explains its displacement in the textual tradition of this breviary.
      2) ff. 399-431v: Commune sanctorum secundum usum parisiensem, mutilated at the end, from De evvangelistis to Commune unius virginis,... auribus meis inestimabiles margaritas//. f. 432r-v ruled but blank.
    - Volume III(1).
      1) ff. 1-6v: Calendar, identical with that in volume I.
      2) ff. 7-201v, Sanctorale; initial loss, probably including the Vigil and Feast of Andrew (29-30 November), now beginning with the Susceptio reliquiarum of Dionysius (4 December) //sanctorum martiris. Ut supra in vesperis. In primo nocturno..., to Tiburtius (14 April); f. 165vb Sequitur ordinatio de festis incidentibus tempore paschali. Notandum est quod si inventio corporum sanctorum Dyonisii sociorumque eius evenerit in die pasche festa sequencia sic celebrari debent.. .; f. 167rb Anno domini M CCC XXIX accidit pascha in festo sancti Georgii. Et fuit ordinatum in capitulo parisiensi de festis celebrandis modo qui sequitur....
      3) ff. 202-218rb: Commune sanctorum secundum usum parisiensem; f. 218rb-219va In conceptionis beate Marie [added in a contemporary hand], ff. 219vb-221 ruled- but blank.
    - Volume III(2)., Parchment, 3 vols.: I, ff. 430; II, ff. 432; III, ff. 400; 310/315 × 220/225 (195/200 × 140) mm. Gatherings of 8 leaves (calendars in gatherings of 6); gatherings mutilated corresponding with the lacunae described in the text; plain horizontal catchwords in the lower right-hand corner. 2 columns of 30 lines; ruled in purple ink. Calligraphic French gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); ink almost black. 6-line illuminated initials in I, ff. 411, 418, 426, to psalms 80, 97, 109, in blue on purple backgrounds enclosing stylized floral patterns, and with border in the inner margin which is now cut away; the folios with presumably similar major initials for psalms 1, 26, 38, 52, and 68 have been removed; 2-line initials, on blue and red penwork, alternately in gold and blue; initials in the text slashed with yellow; rubrics in red and blue; running titles in red minuscule. Generous use of gold leaf.; Bound in French gilt tooled white parchment over paste boards, s. XIX, with the two smaller volumes being bound together; remains of two ties on each volume.
      1) ff. 221v: Four hymns, “Beata nobis gaudia... ,” “Iam Christus astra ascenderat... ,” “Impleta gaudent viscera... ,” “Ihesu nostra redempcio... .”.
      2) ff. 222-366v: Temporale, 2 leaves missing at the beginning and with a lacuna, from In festo Trinitatis to Dom. XXV post pentecosten and the Vigil of St. Andrew //Resp. Benedictus dominus Deus Israel... [f. 223v:| quia Deus donator// [2 leaves missing In festo Sacramenti; f. 224:] //nam verum verbum carnem ....
      3) ff. 366v-368: [Benedictions and commemorations] Sequuntur benedictiones per totum annum; f. 367 Sequuntur memorie communes ab octava penthecostis usque adventum domini dominicis diebus, ad matutinum fit memoria de cruce. f. 368v blank.
      4) ff. 369-400v: Ordinary for the week from Diebus dominicis to Feria IIII, mutilated at beginning and end, //corde ut quid diligitis... misericordia quia tu reddes//.
      Written in the mid-fifteenth century for a wealthy church or wealthy cleric in Paris (”secundum usum parisiensem” passim), perhaps a canon of Notre Dame (III, f. 167, “in capitulo parisiensi”). Belonged to Charles II, duc de Bourbon and constable of France, d. 1527; given by him to a (sieur de l'?) Espinette: II, f. 430, “Ces quatre volumes de breviere ma donnez monseigneur le conestable due de bourbonn' et dauvergne le xiii daoust, presens le sieur destansannes(?) et maitre Jehan de hospital. Espinette” and III, f. 220, “Ce livre ma donne monseigneur le connestable le xiiie jur daoust mil vc xxiii. Espinette,” both notes by the same French cursive hand. This gift (13 August 1523) occurred at the culmination of the rift between the constable and King Francis I; three weeks before, the constable had shifted his allegiance to Francis's enemy the emperor Charles V, and three days after (16 August 1523) Francis attacked the constable's city of Moulins. The gift of the breviary was part of the constable's process of rallying friends to his camp. One of the witnesses, Jean de Lhospital, was the constable's adviser and physician, and father of Michel de Lhospital (d. 1573), chancellor of France. Inside the front cover of vol.I is the description from a Sotheby's catalog which mentions “seven illuminated initials, four with partial borders of conventional flowers and foliage etc., the borders to the remaining three initials cut away”; the four with floral borders have been excised since this description was written. Bought by UCLA from Jacob Schwartz in England, ca. 1950.
      Secundo folio:
      I [Calendar, f. 2] primus inadentem; [Text, f. 8] in breviario ultimum.
      II festum sancti Landerici.
      III [Calendar, f. 2] primus inadentem [Text, f. 8] omnium nostrum salvatoris.
  - BOOK OF HOURS, use of Rouen. France, s. XV2., 170/50.; Fig. 23; Parchment, ff. 122 (first and last are pastedowns, ruled but blank). 183 × 123 (100 × 65) mm. 13 212 (followed by a lacuna) 3-88 94 10-158 (followed by a lacuna) 167. Horizontal catchwords, often trimmed in binding. 16 long lines ruled in purple ink. Late, upright, calligraphic French gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); brown ink. Full-page illuminations on f. 19, Annunication; f. 28v, Visitation of St. Mary to St. Elizabeth; f. 42, Nativity; f. 47, Adoration of the shepherds; f. 50, Adoration of the Kings; f. 52v, Circumcision; f. 55v, Flight into Egypt; f. 61, Coronation of the Virgin Mary; f. 67, David and Nathan; f. 83, Crucifixion; f. 86, Pentecost; f. 89, Three Living and Three Dead; each panel measures 155 × 110 mm, and is surrounded by a border with fantastic and naturalistic animals, conventional flowers, and strawberries on gold background; in the inner and outer margins of the border are included two medallions with scenes related to the subject of the hour. Each page of the calendar has a similar border, with an illuminated panel in the lower margin; the panels on the rectos represent the occupations of the months, and those on the versos illustrate a variety of subjects, mostly biblical, including the baptism of Jesus, Jonah and the whale, Abraham's sacrifice, Noah's Ark, the creation of Eve, Job on his dung heap, Daniel in the lions' den, the Assumption of the Virgin, the drowning of Pharaoh's army. Throughout the book the outer margin of every page is decorated by a band 25-28 mm wide, with conventional flowers and strawberry motifs in green, red, blue, and gold; the decoration is repeated by tracing from the recto to the verso 4-line, 2-line, and 1-line initials in light blue with white highlighting, enclosing floral or strawberry motifs on gold background. Initials in the text slashed with yellow. Rubrics in red minuscule. Line-fillers in gold with ornamental patterns of logs and floral bands.; Bound with a velvet cover (s. XX) over the original bare wooden boards, sewn on 5 thongs.
    1) ff. 1-2v ruled but blank, ff. 3-14v: Full calendar in French with major feasts in gold, the others alternating red and blue; included are the feasts of Ansbert (9 February), Austreberta (10 February), Honorina (27 February), Ursinus, translation (12 June), Martialis (3 July, in gold), Our Lady of the Snow (5 August), Transfiguration (6 August, in gold), Mellonius (22 October), Romanus (23 October, in gold), Clarus (4 November), Edmund Rich (19 November), Ursinus (30 December).
    Scope and Content
    2) ff. 15-18v: //articulos fidei decem precepta legis firmiter tenere... et michi famulo tuo ostende michi... [end of the prayer Obsecro te, Leroquais vol.2, p.346]; Alia oratio, O Intemerata... orbis terrarum. De te enim... [A. Wilmart, Auteurs spirituels et textes dévots du moyen âge latin (Paris, 1932) pp.494-495].
    3) ff. 19-65: Hours of the Virgin, use of Rouen; following lauds are suffrages of the Holy Spirit, the Trinity, Michael, John the Baptist, the Apostles, Lawrence, Nicolas, Catharine of Alexandria, All Saints, and for peace, ff. 65v-66v ruled but blank.
    4) ff. 67-82v: Penitential psalms and litany, including Martialis among the apostles; Blasius, Eutropius, John and Paul, and Firminus among the martyrs; Mellonius, Romanus, Audoenus, Ansbert, Severus, Julianus, Taurinus, Maurus, and Julianus among the confessors; Austreberta and Geneviève among the virgins.
    5) ff. 83-85v: Short hours of the Cross.
    6) ff. 86-88v: Short hours of the Holy Spirit.
    7) ff. 89-115v: Office of the Dead, use of Rouen, ending defectively in the prayer for one's parents,... miserere clementer animabus//.
    8) ff. 116-118v: The first two lines have been erased and the words “parentum meorum” have been added to complete the prayer on f. 115v; the prayer Douce dame de misericorde ... is missing, as is the prologue to the 7 Requests, which now begin Beau sire dieu ie vous requier.,. [Leroquais vol.2, pp.309-310]; Saincte vraye crois aouree... [Sonet 1876]. ff. 119-120v ruled but blank.
    Written in northern France in the second half of the fifteenth century; the saints in the calendar and litany point to Normandy. Washed out pen notes in French on front pastedown and f. 1, with the dates 1631, 1632, 1633, etc. Belonged to the Chicago mail-order merchant Louis E. Asher (1877-1948); printed ex libris inside the front cover. Given to UCLA by William A. Nitze (1876-1957), professor of French literature at UCLA.
    Secundo folio: [Calendar, f. 4] ffevrier
  - HANDBOOK OF CHRONOLOGY. Northern France, s. XVI2., 170/55.; Paper, ff. i + pp. 134 + f. i; 223 × 150 (150 × 100) mm. Gatherings of 4 leaves. 29/33 long lines; frame ruled in ink. Hasty cursive script with some chancery influence; black ink. Initials in red at times on brown penwork. Title in bold red minuscule. Contemporary pagination in arabic numerals.; Contemporary binding in limp parchment.
    pp. 1-134: Brevis Historiae chronologicae a conditu orbis descriptio. lsagoge ad Chronologiam, Vetus est laudare artem quam factitas... [Christus nascitur] omnibus quaeso atque obtestor// (mutilated; notions of chronology and chronological summary from Genesis, through the Assyrians etc., to the Romans).
    Written in the second half of the sixteenth century presumably in northern France. Belonged to the Celestines of Paris; p. 1 bottom, “Celestinorum parisiensium” (s. XVII-XVIII). Source and date of acquisition by UCLA unknown.
    Secundo folio: tempus est dimensum
  - LIFE OF JESUS ACCORDING TO THE GOSPELS in French. Northern France, s. XV2 or XVex., *170/84.; Parchment, ff. iii (i pastedown, ii-iii ruled but blank) + 240 + ii (ii is pastedown); 365 × 265 (255 × 162) mm. 14 (-4, 1 is pastedown) 2-318 Plain horizontal catchwords in the lower right-hand corner; the first four leaves of each fascicule are signed with a letter and roman numerals I to IIII in the lower right-hand corner of the recto. 2 columns of 43 lines; ruled in pale ink (ff. 1-184) and purple ink (ff. ii-iii, 185-240); pricking in the upper, lower and outer margin. Written by two copyists: (i) ff. 1-184, and (ii) ff. 185-240, in developed lettre bâtarde, with some chancery influence in the long flourished ascenders and descenders; ink grayish brown. On f. 3, 8-line initial parted in red and blue on red and blue penwork; similar 4-line initials on ff. 5, 193. 3-line initials of chapters in plain blue, at times on red penwork; 2-line initials in plain red; on ff. 1-2, initials to each entry alternately in red and blue. Titles in red minuscule or in the same ink as the text.; Bound in blind stamped leather (stamps: pelican, lion, flower) over wooden boards, s. XVI.
    1) ff. 1-2; [Chapter list] Ensuit la table et repertoire des chapitres des deux premieres parties de la vie notre, seigneur Jhesu Crist, Premierement. Le premier chapitre parle du prologue ou livre de la vie de Jhesucrist... Le IIII xx et XIIIe, et XXXIe et derrenier de la segonde partie, du serment du quel on se doit garder et de laveugle en Bethsaide enlumine. f. 2v ruled but blank.